<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: programming jobs | Headspring Labs]]></title>
  <link href="http://headspringlabs.com/blog/categories/programming-jobs/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://headspringlabs.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-20T15:46:45-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://headspringlabs.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Headspring Labs]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How we decided on our current vacation policy]]></title>
    <link href="http://headspringlabs.com/blog/how-we-decided-on-our-current-vacation-policy/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://headspringlabs.com/blog/how-we-decided-on-our-current-vacation-policy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img style="margin: 0px 5px 5px 0px; display: inline; float: left" align="left" src="http://www.inc.com/uploaded_files/image/170x170/work-vacation-policy-bkt_3122.jpg"></p>


<p>I very much liked the <a href="https://github.com/blog/1269-the-github-hiring-experience">GitHub write-up</a> on how they hire.&nbsp; It made me think back to a lot of decisions we’ve made at <a href="http://www.headspring.com/">Headspring</a>.&nbsp; One of them is the decision on vacation policy.&nbsp; With a mostly salaried work force, benefits is a big concern, and vacation is one of those.&nbsp; Here, I’ll attempt to share the progression of our vacation policy and how it came about.</p>


<p>First, in 2007/2008 H1, Headspring had just added its 6th employee.&nbsp; The vacation policy was simple but not consistent.&nbsp; On paper, we said “two weeks” for everyone.&nbsp; In practice, we worked too much and didn’t even track days off.&nbsp; Then, by the end of 2008, we grew to over twelve employees and had to modify the policy.&nbsp; If memory serves me, it was in 2009 when we had real conversations and came up with a policy.</p>


<h2>The first real policy</h2>


<p>The idea that arose from having an employee retrospective was that we hired mature professionals, and we didn’t need to have a time-bound, cookie-cutter policy for everyone.&nbsp; The policy that we created them was a “<strong>use as much as you need</strong>” vacation policy.&nbsp; Everyone loved that policy.&nbsp; It communicated to all employees several things.</p>


<ul>
<li>You are a professional
<li>We trust you.</li>
</ul>


<p>We didn’t track days off at all.&nbsp; Over the course of the next two years, we found that this policy left a lot of questions on the table.</p>


<ul>
<li>Ok.&nbsp; I can take as much vacation as I want?&nbsp; Clearly that can’t be the case?
<li>How much vacation is too much?
<li>How much vacation is too little?</li>
</ul>


<p>With highly analytical employees who hold themselves to a high standard, the policy of “whatever” proved to be too ambiguous.&nbsp; Folks did take vacation, but there was always an uneasiness of being unsure of expectations in this area.&nbsp; After another company meeting on the topic – probably around the time of twenty (20) employees, we honed the policy yet again.</p>


<h2>Changing the policy</h2>


<p>First, we re-established a commitment to a 40-hour work week.&nbsp; While some companies boast “we work hard, and we play hard”, we established a “work hard and go home” standard.&nbsp; Sorry.&nbsp; We don’t have a ping-pong table in the office (although our office complex does have horseshoes, sand volleyball, a basketball court, and a Frisbee golf setup).&nbsp; After communicating this, we made the policy for non-billable staff two or three weeks (in addition to the 7 company holidays we have) based on level in the company.&nbsp; The policy for our software engineers (most of the company) became based on billed time.&nbsp; With a standard of a 40-hour work week, we established a percent of the year that we needed to work on client projects in order for the company to remain financially healthy.&nbsp; After all, we make our money by building great custom software for our clients so they can compete in their industries.&nbsp; </p>


<p>The solution, then was to based vacation time on the percent of 2080 hours (a year of 40-hour weeks) that we expected to be billed.&nbsp;&nbsp; In effect, by billing continuously for a couple of months, a week of vacation would then pull the percent of time billed down to where we needed it (80%).&nbsp; This system actually worked very well.&nbsp; Everyone knew exactly how much vacation they could take and still meet their commitment for billed time.&nbsp; I must insert here that we don’t have bonuses for top billers.&nbsp; We are a software engineering firm and not a straight consulting company.&nbsp; Therefore, our goal is not to maximize individual billed time to a client.&nbsp; Our goal is to deliver one awesome software system after another.&nbsp; Often we finish milestones early and leave budget on the table.&nbsp; This is celebrated, not lamented.</p>


<p>With this policy in place, everyone knew what to do, and by tracking our client time, we knew exactly how much time off we could afford per person.&nbsp;&nbsp; One gentleman saved up for himself four weeks of vacation time.</p>


<h2>How the policy broke, and what we did about it</h2>


<p><a href="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/10/CropperCapture63.png"><img style="background-image: none; border-right-width: 0px; margin: 0px 0px 5px 5px; padding-left: 0px; padding-right: 0px; display: inline; float: right; border-top-width: 0px; border-bottom-width: 0px; border-left-width: 0px; padding-top: 0px" title="CropperCapture[63]" border="0" alt="CropperCapture[63]" align="right" src="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/10/CropperCapture63_thumb.png" width="244" height="140"></a>This policy carried us to early 2012.&nbsp; Now, at 30 employees, we have a different policy.&nbsp; The currently policy is much simpler and requires much less math.&nbsp; It is much more in alignment with our philosophy of “light on policy, heavy on judgment.”&nbsp;&nbsp; We have now changed the policy for our software engineers to&nbsp; be the following: 80% client work, 10% non-client company time, and 10% personal time.&nbsp; That means that 10% of the year, it’s yours.&nbsp; With a 52-week year, it is 5.2 weeks.&nbsp; We have found that most people don’t take 5.2 weeks of vacation per year, so that is enough for sick days, other stuff, and small bits of time off spread throughout the year as well.&nbsp; Then, the 10% of company time covers our staff meetings, fun quarterly off-sites, and other stuff.&nbsp; We put that policy in place because we found that a few people we uneasy about taking vacation because they were afraid of bench time.&nbsp; Our policy had not taken that into account.&nbsp; We wanted everyone to take vacation, and now the current policy ensures that.</p>


<h2>What will it be next?</h2>


<p>I have no idea.&nbsp; We’ve tweaked it over the years, and if we find another downside to the current policy, we’ll tweak it again.&nbsp; The good news is that we have such great people who live the company values, that they tend to speak up if something isn’t right.&nbsp; One of our company values is honest communication (candor), and they do a great job of living this one out.&nbsp; </p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
