<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: conferences | Headspring Labs]]></title>
  <link href="http://headspringlabs.com/blog/categories/conferences/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://headspringlabs.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-15T23:13:23-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://headspringlabs.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Headspring Labs]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SXSW Interactive 2012: Over and Out]]></title>
    <link href="http://headspringlabs.com/blog/sxsw-interactive-2012-over-and-out/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://headspringlabs.com/blog/sxsw-interactive-2012-over-and-out</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last Friday I took to the Austin Convention Center for the five day frenzy known as SXSW Interactive.  Basically, I made this meme summing up my time spent downtown quite nicely:</p>


<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.headspring.com/2012/03/sxsw-interactive-2012-over-and-out/sxswwhatiactuallydo" rel="attachment wp-att-4127"><img class="size-large wp-image-4127 aligncenter" title="sxswWhatIActuallyDo" src="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/sxswWhatIActuallyDo-1024x651.png" alt="" width="517" height="329" /><!--more--></a></p>


<p>The lines were insane! I waited three hours to pick up my badge.  However, the rest of the time I experienced very little trouble getting into the panels I wanted to see or any of the other events on my schedule.  I would have been lost without the iPhone and iPad app.</p>


<p>During the event, I exercised the full use of all available resources:  time, research, relationships, and drink tickets.  I kept a full schedule each day, beginning at 9:00 AM and lasting into the late evening.  During the day, I made it to as many presentations, panels, and discussions as possible - usually 3 to 4.  The first few days there, I was being carried by adrenaline, and made the mistake of neglecting breaks.  Next year will be different.</p>


<p>My favorite panels and presentations were those that were well thought out and prepared.  I really liked Ray Kurzweil’s discussion about AI and singularity, Jen Pahlka’s presentation on Code for America, and the panel on Agile Apps: Effective Moblie and Native Development.  Here are some more photos:</p>


<p>&nbsp;</p>


<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.headspring.com/2012/03/sxsw-interactive-2012-over-and-out/photo-3" rel="attachment wp-att-4117"><img class="size-medium wp-image-4117 aligncenter" title="ray kurzweil sxsw" src="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/photo-3-300x224.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="224" /></a><a href="http://www.headspring.com/2012/03/sxsw-interactive-2012-over-and-out/photo-4" rel="attachment wp-att-4118"><img class="size-medium wp-image-4118 aligncenter" title="jen pahlka sxsw" src="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/photo-4-300x224.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="224" /></a><a href="http://www.headspring.com/2012/03/sxsw-interactive-2012-over-and-out/photo-5" rel="attachment wp-att-4119"><img class="size-medium wp-image-4119 aligncenter" title="ogilvy notes sxsw" src="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/photo-5-300x224.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="224" /></a><a href="http://www.headspring.com/2012/03/sxsw-interactive-2012-over-and-out/photo-8" rel="attachment wp-att-4120"><img class="size-medium wp-image-4120 aligncenter" title="sxsw presentation crowd" src="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/photo-8-300x224.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="224" /></a></p>


<p>In between scheduled events, I would browse the trade show floor, designated networking lounges and workshops. I reserved some time each day to check in with fellow industry friends, and exchange information on who’s who and where the free food was.</p>


<p>The panels and discussions exceeded my expectations.  The content was current, interesting, and informative, and the presentations - led by credible industry influencers – were well prepared and polished.  Topics ranged from highly technical, to quirky and imaginative, or challenging and perceptive.  I took lots of notes.</p>


<p>With over 30,000 attendees, there was no shortage of opportunity to network.  I made it a point to get to know the people around me at events, sitting next to me during presentations, or evening those that I stood in line with.  Because SXSW is designed to encourage community and relationship building, I found that most people were very open to participating in conversation when prompted. The parties each evening were great for meeting up, too, although we tried to keep the business chatter light.</p>


<p>However the <em>best</em> part of the conference was supporting the<a href="http://www.headspring.com/2012/02/headspring-shows-some-love-at-knowbilitys-austin-air"> Headspring Hurwitzes</a> as they received 2<sup>nd</sup> Place in the Formula One division of Knowbility’s AIR Interactive Competition.  I’m so proud of my team!  Here is a picture of them with their award:</p>


<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.headspring.com/2012/03/sxsw-interactive-2012-over-and-out/photo-6" rel="attachment wp-att-4123"><img class="size-medium wp-image-4123 aligncenter" title="headspring second place AIR Interactive" src="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/photo-6-300x224.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="224" /></a></p>


<p>So, now that it’s over I’ll be catching up on my beauty rest and rehydrating.  I’m looking forward to next year!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dallas Day of Dot NET: Get Nerdy With It]]></title>
    <link href="http://headspringlabs.com/blog/dallas-day-of-dot-net-get-nerdy-with-it/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-08T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://headspringlabs.com/blog/dallas-day-of-dot-net-get-nerdy-with-it</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The bags are packed and we’re ready to head out for Dallas Day of Dot NET.  We've heard through event organizers that over 500 people are expected to attend.  Woo Hoo!  Half of our team is going, including President, Jeffrey Palermo, sporting a fresh polo from his recently bestowed and 7<sup>th</sup> consecutive Microsoft MVP title.</p>


<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.headspring.com/2012/03/dallas-day-of-dot-net-get-nerdy-with-it/photo-2" rel="attachment wp-att-4036"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-4036" title="Katie and Jeffrey heading to Dallas Day of Dot NET" src="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/photo-2-224x300.jpg" alt="" width="224" height="300" /></a><a href="http://www.headspring.com/2012/03/dallas-day-of-dot-net-get-nerdy-with-it/photo-1" rel="attachment wp-att-4037"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-4037" title="photo (1)" src="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/photo-1-224x300.jpg" alt="" width="224" height="300" /><!--more--></a></p>


<p>Obviously, we’re super excited about the main event:  keynote speaker Scott Hanselman.  Hanselman is well known for many things, most notably his evangelism for Microsoft and all things .NET.  His popular weekly podcast series <em>Hanselminutes</em> and blog <em>Scott Hanselman’s Computer Zen</em> will be the source of inspiration for his presentation titled <em>Making Your Blog Suck Less</em>.</p>


<p>The posted <a href="http://dallasdayofdotnet.com/dallasdayofdotnet/Home/Agenda">agenda</a> doesn’t include any abstracts. Lucky for you, a few Headspringers are presenting and provided me with their details:</p>


<p style="padding-left: 30px;"><strong>Jeffrey Palermo: </strong><em>Developing for Business Intelligence</em></p>


<p style="padding-left: 30px;">With Microsoft aligning several of its products to serve BI needs, .Net developers are left with little support for providing analytical answers from data stored in system databases.  Even reports are often just formatted query results on a screen.  Business intelligence is about deriving knowledge from your data, not just view raw data.  From fact tables to star schemas to methods of visualization, Visual Studio doesn't provide much support for these important and enabling concepts for BI.  This session will introduce developers to the fundamentals of BI development and the basic tools and techniques they can use to start extracting intelligence from their data.</p>


<p style="padding-left: 30px;"><strong>Jimmy Bogard: </strong><em>Keeping Integration Sane with NServiceBus</em></p>


<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Building apps used to be simple when we just needed to push data into a database. However, more and more we see our applications needing to communicate with other external applications via REST, SOAP, or for the less fortunate, flat files. We can assume these external services are always 100% up, but inevitably, someone trips over the cord and communication fails. Often, recovering from these kinds of failures are the hardest to recover from, causing developers and the business alike significant heartburn.</p>


<p style="padding-left: 30px;">In this session we'll examine the common causes for failures integrating with other systems. We'll look at the basics of messaging and alternate UI interaction models to accommodate failure. Finally, we'll dig in to NServiceBus and see how NServiceBus kicks the problems of flaky integration to the curb once and for all.</p>


<p style="padding-left: 30px;"><strong>Tim Thomas: </strong><em>Building Games with .NET and XNA Game Studio</em></p>


<p style="padding-left: 30px;"><em></em>Developing your own game can be a daunting task. In this session, you’ll see how easy it is to get started from scratch with XNA Game Studio 4.0, the latest version of Microsoft’s multi-platform game creation toolkit. You’ll be introduced to the developer-friendly—and free!—community resources available for building games for the PC, Xbox, and Windows Phone and learn more about this industry-changing game development technology.</p>


<p style="padding-left: 30px;"><strong>Ryan Vice:  </strong><em>State Management in Windows 8 Metro Applications</em></p>


<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Metro introduces a new application lifecyle in which your application could be terminated at anytime. This example driven session will explore how to write applications that sucessfully manage persisted, session and view state in the Metro environment allowing you to provide a good user experience for your end users. The concepts apply to all Metro development but will be demonstrated using C# and XAML.</p>


<p>After that, Headspringers disperse to “get nerdy with it.”  If you’re in town, plan on stopping by to visit Katie in the sponsor area.  She’ll have swag, stickers, and as always, good conversation.  Pick up one of these beauties for your car bumper, and share the photo on our <a href="http://www.facebook.com/pages/Headspring/280556282000204">Facebook wall</a>!</p>


<p><a href="http://www.headspring.com/2012/03/dallas-day-of-dot-net-get-nerdy-with-it/photo" rel="attachment wp-att-4038"><img class="size-medium wp-image-4038 aligncenter" title="Headspring bumper stickers" src="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/photo-224x300.jpg" alt="" width="224" height="300" /></a></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Make the Most of SXSWi for Free]]></title>
    <link href="http://headspringlabs.com/blog/make-the-most-of-sxswi-for-free/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-06T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://headspringlabs.com/blog/make-the-most-of-sxswi-for-free</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The second week of March is upon us, and I could not be more excited.</p>


<p>SXSW Interactive is going to be bigger and better than ever – over 19,000 are expected to attend this year.   I’m really looking forward to being a part of it.  Even the Juggalos will be there!  Juggalos and Bruce Springsteen featured in the same event; I never thought I would see the day.</p>


<p>If you have a badge, make sure to find me and say hello. In between panels, I plan to visit the Microsoft and Beacon Lounges or browse the Trade Show and ScreenBurn Arcade.  Here’s my schedule:   <a href="http://schedule.sxsw.com/2012/user_events/user_60347">http://schedule.sxsw.com/2012/user_events/user_60347</a></p>


<p>However, if you don’t have badge, there is still plenty of opportunity to get in on the action.  Of course, I’ve made a list:<!--more--></p>


<p><strong>Thursday, March 8<sup>th</sup>: </strong><a href="http://door64.com/sxsw2012">Door64 Pre-SXSW Interactive Party</a></p>


<p>Techies don’t usually need a party to prove how fun they are, but an open bar sponsored by Dell, Intel, and CyrusOne never hurts.  Along with free booze, there will be two bands, and Dell is giving out free laptops and other devices for door prizes. Tickets are cheap ($20) and half off if you’re an Austin Cloud User Goup member.  A steal of a deal!</p>


<p><strong>Friday, March 9<sup>th</sup>:</strong> <a href="https://www.facebook.com/events/301931889872103">Refresh Austin’s SXSW Kickoff Lunch</a></p>


<p>For the fourth year in a row, Refresh Austin has organized an opportunity for folks to mingle and catch up with Refreshers from all over the world.  It’s not sponsored, so you’ll have to pick up your own tab.  However, this is a great opportunity to meet up with badge-holding friends from out-of-town, and convince them to get a job at your company in Austin!</p>


<p><strong>Sunday, March 11<sup>th</sup>: </strong><a href="http://www.eventida.com/events/2012_dewey_ceremony_air-interactive_awards/#SXSWparty">Dewey Awards Ceremony</a></p>


<p>This event is also free, and is co-presented by our friends at Knowbility.  The party will honor 10 media do-gooders with tons of food, drink, and music.  Also, Knowbility will announce the winners for SXSW Interactive AIR.  We’re keeping our fingers crossed for the team of Headspringers that participated in the competition!</p>


<p><strong>Monday, March 12<sup>th</sup>: </strong><a href="http://garann.com/allgirlhacknight/2012/cli.html">Austin All-Girl Dev Brunch</a></p>


<p>The Austin All-Girl Hack Night and Girl Develop It groups have organized a brunch for techie chicks to get together and celebrate their awesomeness.  This year, Headspring is sponsoring because 1) we love All Girl Hack Night 2) we really love the Bloody Mary’s at Frank.  If you’re a girl and you love to code, I strongly encourage you to check this one out. And it’s totally free!</p>


<p>As always, we’ll continue to keep our community events calendar updated with these events and more.</p>


<p>If you know of any other non-badge required events going on during sxswi, please post in our comments.  Happy hunting!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
