<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Blog | Headspring Labs]]></title>
  <link href="http://headspringlabs.com/blog/categories/blog/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://headspringlabs.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-15T23:13:23-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://headspringlabs.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Headspring Labs]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[MVC Custom Unobtrusive Validator Attribute (Date Range Validation)]]></title>
    <link href="http://headspringlabs.com/blog/mvc-custom-unobtrusive-validator-attribute-date-range-validation/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://headspringlabs.com/blog/mvc-custom-unobtrusive-validator-attribute-date-range-validation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are some useful attributes in MVC that help render dynamic unobtrusive validation to the browser.   The more you can accomplish by simply adding an attribute to a property on a view model the less duplication of JavaScript you have to manage.  Out of the “MVC” box validation for date ranges would require custom JavaScript.  If you have multiple pages that all need to validate ranges, either from the current date or from another date property on your view model, how about having an attribute that you can use to handles this?</p>


<p>In this blog I’m going to cover:</p>


<ul>
<li>Creating a Custom MVC Validation Attribute</li>
<li>Creating a  Client Validation Rule</li>
<li>Creating and wiring up the unobtrusive JavaScript to do the validation</li>
</ul>


<p>First to create a validation Attribute you need to inherit from the <strong>ValidationAttribute</strong>.  To make this validation available on the client you need to implement the <strong>IClientValidatable</strong> interface.  The <strong>ValidationAttribute</strong> is where you define the settable properties that can be used by the View Model.  To handle the validation server side you can override the <strong>IsValid</strong> method to execute your validation logic.  The <strong>IClientValidatable</strong> interface exposes the <strong>GetClientValidationRules</strong> method.  The validation rules are parameters that will be provided to your JavaScript as an array.  The <strong>ModelClientValidationRule </strong>is where you define the Rules/Settings that the <strong>ValidationAttribute</strong> will provide based upon what was supplied when the attribute was applied to a property on a View Model.</p>


<p>Lets look at some code before we go to far.</p>


<p><div><script src='https://gist.github.com/5200208.js'></script>
<noscript><pre><code></code></pre></noscript></div>
</p>


<p>The <strong>DataComparerAttribute</strong> exposes the properties that will be used when the attribute is applied to a property on a View Model.  Notice that the <strong>ModelClientValidationRangeDateRule</strong> exposes the same properties and maps to the validation attribute.  This type is created in the <strong>GetClientValidationRules</strong> method which creates the <strong>ValidationParameters</strong> that will be passed to the Client JavaScript validation method.  Now we have enough to implement the server side <strong>IsValid</strong> method and the client side JavaScript to handle the unobtrusive validation.</p>


<p>With the attribute defined the JavaScript can be created.  The client JavaScript function is linked through the <strong>ModelClientValidationRule.ValidationType</strong> string property.  In this validator the <strong>ValidationType</strong> was set to <em>“rangeDate”</em>.  This value is what we will use to add to the JQuery validator.  There are two JQuery validator concepts we need to link to the magic string <em>“rangeDate”</em> .  The <strong>$.validator.unobtrusive.adapters </strong>which is where MVC will supply the View Model rules from the <strong>GetClientValidationRules</strong> method and the <strong>$.validator.addMethod </strong>which is where the actual JavaScript validation function is defined.</p>


<p><div><script src='https://gist.github.com/5205136.js'></script>
<noscript><pre><code></code></pre></noscript></div>
</p>


<p>Notice the signature of the <strong>$.validator.unobtrusive.adapters </strong>(line 4).  This is where the same array defined in the <strong>ModelClientValidationRangeDateRule.ValidationParameters</strong> lines up to the client code.  MVC will expect the C# and JavaScript to match.  Notice the date format being used to supply the <em>“minDate”</em> and <em>“maxDate”</em>.  Since date formatting can be complicated having the server side format match the client side format helps to make the validation more predictable.</p>


<p>With the attribute complete now we can apply it to our View Model and see it in action.  This validator is designed to do validation based upon a Max Date and a Min Date.  For Min and Max the choices are either a sibling property on the View Model (MinDateSelector and MaxDateSelector) or an interval from DateTime.Now (MinDateAddDaysFromNow, MaxDateAddDaysFromNow).  The *DateSelector will be used to get the current value from the property on the View Model.  When the server side <strong>IsValid</strong> is executed Reflection is used to get the property value.  When the client side JavaScript is executed JQuery is used to get the value from a HTML element on the browser.</p>


<p><div><script src='https://gist.github.com/5205378.js'></script>
<noscript><pre><code></code></pre></noscript></div>
</p>


<p>In the above usage of the attribute the BirthDate must be from January 1st 2013 through the current Date and Time the validation is executed.</p>


<h3>Summary</h3>


<p>Adding custom validation to MVC is useful in reducing duplication of code.  As you can see it’s not all that complicated to do.  The validation methods for server side and client side validation risk having different logic and need to use different mechanisms to get property values.  Reflection and JQuery make this easy enough but there are still gotchas that need to be considered.  When your using JQuery to select a value on a page you need to make sure your selector is unique.  If in our case we have more than one View Model loaded on the page the JQuery Selector could return another html elements value.  I hope this gets you started and can open up some new possibilities for validation.</p>


<p>To see the full example and source code go to <a title="https://github.com/jdmgomoo/MVC-CustomAttributes" href="https://github.com/jdmgomoo/MVC-CustomAttributes">https://github.com/jdmgomoo/MVC-CustomAttributes</a></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Meet Headspring: Angel Rivera]]></title>
    <link href="http://headspringlabs.com/blog/meet-headspring-angel-rivera/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://headspringlabs.com/blog/meet-headspring-angel-rivera</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Looking for a warmer place to live and the best city to raise a family, Angel Rivera touched down in Austin in 2010 with his wife. The couple grew their family with a son in 2011, and he is very proud. “My son takes my breath away. There’s no getting used to it, and there are new adventures every day. It gives me a whole new way of looking at life.” Angel joined our Headspring team in January, and we’re happy to have him!</p>


<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="size-medium wp-image-6483 aligncenter" alt="" src="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/Angel1-200x300.jpg" width="200" height="300" /></p>


<p><b>What did you do before coming to Headspring?</b></p>


<p>I was born and raised in Puerto Rico where I went to college and graduated with a B.A. in graphic design.  I moved to Ohio when I was 21 years old. From there, I spent several years in Iowa, Kansas and Minnesota before I moved here for the long haul.</p>


<p><b>What do you love most about Austin?</b></p>


<p>The culture: laid-back, diverse, and relaxed. You can find everything from high-class restaurants to ones with a pet-friendly patio. There’s a little bit of everything for everyone.</p>


<p><b>What attracted you to Headspring?</b></p>


<p>I was attracted to the opportunity to work with a close-knit team, to the company culture, and to the opportunity to jump into the ever-changing software industry. I’m thankful for the opportunity!</p>


<p><b>How do you gauge “time well spent?"</b></p>


<p>When I’m being productive.</p>


<p><b>Who is your role model?</b></p>


<p>I would have to say my parents.  They were both very young when I was born. With no education, it must have been incredibly hard for them to raise both my sister and me, but they pulled it off.</p>


<p><b>What is your role at Headspring?</b></p>


<p>I’m a Business Development Consultant. I look for companies that would benefit from our services and who we can establish a strong business relationship with. A win-win.</p>


<p><b>What do you hope to accomplish professionally and personally in the next 5 years?</b></p>


<p>In the 11 years since Headspring was created, we have grown tremendously. I want to make sure Headspring continues to grow and expand so that every company out there knows how awesome we are.</p>


<p>Personally, I want to buy my mom a house in Puerto Rico. She is renting a small one-bedroom apartment right now and I think it’s time she has her own place again.</p>


<p><b>What do you enjoy doing in your free time?</b></p>


<p>I love watching movies and TV shows. The last movie I saw at the theater was Cabin in the Woods. I also enjoy playing video games (if I can find the time), playing my guitar, spending time with my family, going to the park and trying new restaurants. We’re foodies, and I especially love Thai food.</p>


<p><b>What’s your favorite Puerto Rican dish?</b></p>


<p>Rice, beans and chicken with fried plantains. There’s only one Puerto Rican restaurant – Chagos Restaurant – here. Their food is good but frankly, I cook better than they do, so I’m never homesick for Puerto Rican food!</p>


<p><b>What’s a tool you can’t live without?</b></p>


<p>Google Navigator, because I have a horrible sense of direction! I went to Puerto Rico during the Christmas holiday, and I got lost constantly because Google Maps doesn’t work there!</p>


<p><b>Any social media links?</b></p>


<p>Tweet me at <a href="http://twitter.com/angelrivera_pr" target="_blank">@angelrivera_pr</a>.</p>


<p>&nbsp;</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Creating Windows Installers with the WiX Toolset - Summary]]></title>
    <link href="http://headspringlabs.com/blog/creating-windows-installers-with-the-wix-toolset-summary/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://headspringlabs.com/blog/creating-windows-installers-with-the-wix-toolset-summary</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<address>This article is part of a series exploring how to create installers for Windows software.  Here's the complete contents of the series.</address>


<address><a href="http://www.headspring.com/nolan/creating-windows-installers-with-the-wix-toolset-part-01/">Part 1 – What Kinds of Software Projects Benefit From an Installer?</a><br />
<a href="http://www.headspring.com/nolan/creating-windows-installers-with-the-wix-toolset-part-02/">Part 2 – An Overview Of Windows Installer and its Features</a><br />
<a href="http://www.headspring.com/nolan/creating-windows-installers-with-the-wix-toolset-part-03/">Part 3 – Tooling Options for Building Installers</a><br />
<a href="http://www.headspring.com/nolan/creating-windows-installers-with-the-wix-toolset-part-04/">Part 4 – The Windows Installer Runtime Sequence</a><br />
<a href="http://www.headspring.com/nolan/creating-windows-installers-with-the-wix-toolset-part-5/">Part 5 – The Contents of an MSI</a><br />
<a href="http://www.headspring.com/nolan/creating-windows-installers-with-the-wix-toolset-part-6/">Part 6 – The Structure of a WiX File</a><br />
<a href="http://www.headspring.com/nolan/creating-windows-installers-with-the-wix-toolset-part-7/">Part 7 – Generating an MSI Package From Your WiX</a><br />
<a href="http://www.headspring.com/nolan/creating-windows-installers-with-the-wix-toolset-part-8/">Part 8 – Troubleshooting Installer Runtime Problems</a><br />
<a href="http://www.headspring.com/nolan/creating-windows-installers-with-the-wix-toolset-summary/">Part 9 - Summary</a><br />
</address>


<p><br/></p>


<h2>Summing It All Up</h2>


<p>We've covered a lot of ground over this series. We've talked about what kind of projects benefit from having an installer and why you should consider making one. We've learned what Windows Installer actually is (a feature of the Windows operating system) and what some of the tooling options for creating installers are. We've explored the sequence of events that occur when installing a package as well as the contents of an actual MSI package. We've dived into the basic structure of a WiX file and how an understanding of the Windows Installer concepts makes authoring WiX files easier. Coming full circle, we've created an installer package from WiX source with the WiX tooling.</p>


<p>There's certainly a lot left we could discuss: automatic file harvesting, custom actions, etc. However I haven't had much feedback on the series up to this point: Windows Installer is a niche topic in software development, especially with the rise of the web. I'm thinking about moving on to other topics.</p>


<h2>Last Call...</h2>


<p>Is there something you want to know that I haven't covered yet? This is the time to leave feedback in the comments if you want to see more articles in this series. Thanks for reading with me!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Creating Windows Installers with the WiX Toolset Part 8]]></title>
    <link href="http://headspringlabs.com/blog/creating-windows-installers-with-the-wix-toolset-part-8/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://headspringlabs.com/blog/creating-windows-installers-with-the-wix-toolset-part-8</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<address>This article is part of a series exploring how to create installers for Windows software.  Here's the complete contents of the series.</address>


<address><a href="http://www.headspring.com/nolan/creating-windows-installers-with-the-wix-toolset-part-01/">Part 1 – What Kinds of Software Projects Benefit From an Installer?</a><br />
<a href="http://www.headspring.com/nolan/creating-windows-installers-with-the-wix-toolset-part-02/">Part 2 – An Overview Of Windows Installer and its Features</a><br />
<a href="http://www.headspring.com/nolan/creating-windows-installers-with-the-wix-toolset-part-03/">Part 3 – Tooling Options for Building Installers</a><br />
<a href="http://www.headspring.com/nolan/creating-windows-installers-with-the-wix-toolset-part-04/">Part 4 – The Windows Installer Runtime Sequence</a><br />
<a href="http://www.headspring.com/nolan/creating-windows-installers-with-the-wix-toolset-part-5/">Part 5 – The Contents of an MSI</a><br />
<a href="http://www.headspring.com/nolan/creating-windows-installers-with-the-wix-toolset-part-6/">Part 6 – The Structure of a WiX File</a><br />
<a href="http://www.headspring.com/nolan/creating-windows-installers-with-the-wix-toolset-part-7/">Part 7 – Generating an MSI Package From Your WiX</a><br />
<a href="http://www.headspring.com/nolan/creating-windows-installers-with-the-wix-toolset-part-8/">Part 8 – Troubleshooting Installer Runtime Problems</a><br />
<a href="http://www.headspring.com/nolan/creating-windows-installers-with-the-wix-toolset-summary/">Part 9 - Summary</a><br />
</address>


<p><br/><span style="font-size: 13px;">This entry describes how to enable diagnostic logging when running an installer and some tools for analyzing the output.</span></p>


<h2>Troubleshooting Runtime Problems - When All Else Fails, Print</h2>


<p>Let’s face it: things don’t always work the way they’re supposed to and installers are no different. If you’re making anything more complex than the simple Hello World example we’ve been using in this series, you’re going to run into situation where something doesn’t work quite right and you can’t figure out why.</p>


<p>Probably the world’s oldest debugging technique that predates debuggers themselves is printing a line of output with the current program location and variable values at runtime.  Windows installer doesn’t provide a native way to do this in the UI itself, but we do have the next best thing: log files.</p>


<h2>Enabling Logging During an Installation</h2>


<pre>Use msiexec (builts into Windows) to run your msi in a diagnostic mode and get a log file. Here’s an example invocation that asks for verbose logging into a file called HelloWorld.log: &#160;%windir%\system32\msiexec.exe /i artifacts\installer\HelloWorld.msi /l*v HelloWorld.log</pre>


<p>The content of the log for our simple Hello World is 749 lines. I’m obviously not going to paste it in here, but I will briefly describe some of the contents you’ll see in a log file.</p>


<ul>
<li>Machine environment settings, such as whether the computer can have patches applied or not</li>
<li>The value of properties (variables), such as the install directory</li>
<li>The beginning and end of the execute stage</li>
<li>The value of all properties at the end of the installation</li>
</ul>


<p>Most importantly, any errors that occurred should be contained here as well. You can simply search through the log for “error”.</p>


<h2>Tools for Analyzing a Log File</h2>


<p>I have not gotten a large amount of use from the tool I’m about to introduce, but I want to make you aware of it because it might be valuable to you.</p>


<p>The Windows SDK includes a utility reader for installer logs located at %PROGRAMFILES%\Microsoft SDKs\Windows\v7.1\Bin (or something similar). The utility is named WiLogUtl.exe. When you start the log analyzer, you’ll need to browse to your log file and open it. I’ve already done that step in the screenshot below.</p>


<p><a href="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/logAnalyzer.png"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-6466" alt="logAnalyzer" src="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/logAnalyzer.png" width="638" height="335" /></a></p>


<p>When you click Analyze, you’re taken to another screen.</p>


<p><a href="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/analysis.png"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-6467" alt="analysis" src="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/analysis.png" width="669" height="545" /></a></p>


<p>The most prominent UI element at the top is an errors list. Our log doesn’t have any, but this view makes it easy to see them all in one place.<br />
We also have a variety of options on the right. States will show you the detected status of the features in your package – whether they are already installed or not. Properties will give you a list of all the properties (variables) and their values in your installer.</p>


<p>The HTML Log is rather nice because it will color code all the log entries by category, and provide controls for navigating between any errors.</p>


<p><a href="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/htmlLogFile.png"><img class="alignnone size-large wp-image-6468" alt="htmlLogFile" src="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/htmlLogFile-970x709.png" width="970" height="709" /></a></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Creating Windows Installers with the WiX Toolset Part 7]]></title>
    <link href="http://headspringlabs.com/blog/creating-windows-installers-with-the-wix-toolset-part-7/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://headspringlabs.com/blog/creating-windows-installers-with-the-wix-toolset-part-7</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<address>This article is part of a series exploring how to create installers for Windows software.  Here's the complete contents of the series.</address>


<address><a href="http://www.headspring.com/nolan/creating-windows-installers-with-the-wix-toolset-part-01/">Part 1 – What Kinds of Software Projects Benefit From an Installer?</a><br />
<a href="http://www.headspring.com/nolan/creating-windows-installers-with-the-wix-toolset-part-02/">Part 2 – An Overview Of Windows Installer and its Features</a><br />
<a href="http://www.headspring.com/nolan/creating-windows-installers-with-the-wix-toolset-part-03/">Part 3 – Tooling Options for Building Installers</a><br />
<a href="http://www.headspring.com/nolan/creating-windows-installers-with-the-wix-toolset-part-04/">Part 4 – The Windows Installer Runtime Sequence</a><br />
<a href="http://www.headspring.com/nolan/creating-windows-installers-with-the-wix-toolset-part-5/">Part 5 – The Contents of an MSI</a><br />
<a href="http://www.headspring.com/nolan/creating-windows-installers-with-the-wix-toolset-part-6/">Part 6 – The Structure of a WiX File</a><br />
<a href="http://www.headspring.com/nolan/creating-windows-installers-with-the-wix-toolset-part-7/">Part 7 – Generating an MSI Package From Your WiX</a><br />
<a href="http://www.headspring.com/nolan/creating-windows-installers-with-the-wix-toolset-part-8/">Part 8 – Troubleshooting Installer Runtime Problems</a><br />
<a href="http://www.headspring.com/nolan/creating-windows-installers-with-the-wix-toolset-summary/">Part 9 - Summary</a><br />
</address>


<p><br/><br />
This post explains how to create an MSI installer from the WiX files you’ve written from either the command line or within Visual Studio.</p>


<h2>The Missing Magic</h2>


<p>So we’ve discussed how an MSI is an installer package that Windows can process and taken a peek at what the insides of an MSI looks like, and then we’ve examined a simple WiX file that can be used to create an MSI and how WiX schema is heavily tied to the entities of Windows Installer.  But we don’t quite have the complete picture yet – how do we magically get our MSI once we’ve authored some WiX?</p>


<h2><a href="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/magicHappensHere.png"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-6459" alt="magicHappensHere" src="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/magicHappensHere.png" width="800" height="233" /><br />
</a>It's Just A Compiler</h2>


<p>So the answer is 42.  <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Answer_to_The_Ultimate_Question_of_Life,_the_Universe,_and_Everything#Answer_to_the_Ultimate_Question_of_Life.2C_the_Universe.2C_and_Everything_.2842.29">Just kidding.</a>  The answer is that the WiX toolset comes with its own compiler and linker tools.  If you’ve ever set up an automated build, this is the WiX equivalent of MsBuild.exe (or if you’re really hard core, csc.exe).  Most of the tooling in WiX is related to candles in some fashion (WiX sounds like “wicks”, the burning portion of a candle), so you might find it amusing to learn the name of the compiler is “candle”, and the linker is called “light”.</p>


<p><a href="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/candleAndLight.png"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-6460" alt="candleAndLight" src="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/candleAndLight.png" width="499" height="299" /></a></p>


<p>There are two ways you can run the compiler:  through the command line, or as an integrated extension of Visual Studio.  I’ll discuss both below.</p>


<h2>From the Command Line</h2>


<p>This is my preferred method.  Usually when I’m building an installer, I’ve had to do some PowerShell scripting to stage the output that I want to be packaged up by the installer.  This is usually artifacts like help files, shortcut icons, and so forth.  This is also the primary method for getting an installer compilation rolled into your automated build (you might be able to use Votive with TFS, you’ll have to verify that with someone that willingly uses TFS).</p>


<p>Invocation looks something like this in a simple bat file:</p>


<pre>rem If we don&#39;t specify an output directory, the wixobj files will get dumped in the current working directory of the bat file</pre>


<pre>tools\wix\candle.exe src\installer\HelloWorld.wxs -out artifacts\wix\</pre>


<pre>tools\wix\light.exe artifacts\wix\HelloWorld.wixobj -out artifacts\wix\HelloWorld.msi</pre>


<pre></pre>


<pre>rem Move the final output for exposure to CI build or shared network folder</pre>


<pre>copy artifacts\wix\HelloWorld.msi artifacts\installer</pre>


<h2> Inside Visual Studio</h2>


<p>The WiX tooling comes with a Visual Studio extension called Votive.  I mentioned it earlier how you can use it to get IntelliSense when editing your WiX files.  Votive also makes it possible to compile your WiX when doing a build in Visual Studio.</p>


<p>If you examine the properties of your WiX project, you’ll find a host of options for controlling your compilation.</p>


<p>The Installer tab lets you name your output file, and choose alternate output types if you happen to need something besides MSI (if you don’t know otherwise, then stick with MSI).</p>


<p><a href="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/buildTab.png"><img class="alignnone size-large wp-image-6461" alt="buildTab" src="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/buildTab-970x335.png" width="970" height="335" /></a></p>


<p>&nbsp;</p>


<p>The Build tab allows you to specify values for your preprocessor variables (WiX supports preprocessing similar to C and C++ compilers), and where to place your output.</p>


<p><a href="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/buildTab1.png"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-6462" alt="buildTab" src="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/buildTab1.png" width="673" height="642" /></a></p>


<p>&nbsp;</p>


<p>The Tool Settings tab can be used to ignore ICE validation on your package (although I’d suggest leaving it on, you always want to know about potential problems), and pass additional arguments to the compiler and linker.</p>


<p><a href="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/toolSettings.png"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-6463" alt="toolSettings" src="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/toolSettings.png" width="655" height="521" /></a></p>


<p>&nbsp;</p>


<p>When you compile the project in Visual Studio, if you look carefully at the build output you’ll see that it’s simply invoking candle and light for you under the hood:</p>


<p><a href="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/votiveOutput.png"><img class="alignnone size-large wp-image-6464" alt="votiveOutput" src="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/votiveOutput-970x158.png" width="970" height="158" /></a></p>


<p>&nbsp;</p>


<p>If you do use Votive, you probably won’t want to build the installer in debug configuration.  Otherwise you’ll have to wait for an installer to build every time you recompile the solution.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
