<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Get To Know a Headspringer | Headspring Labs]]></title>
  <link href="http://headspringlabs.com/blog/categories/get-to-know-a-headspringer/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://headspringlabs.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-17T18:29:29-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://headspringlabs.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Headspring Labs]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Meet Headspring: Angel Rivera]]></title>
    <link href="http://headspringlabs.com/blog/meet-headspring-angel-rivera/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://headspringlabs.com/blog/meet-headspring-angel-rivera</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Looking for a warmer place to live and the best city to raise a family, Angel Rivera touched down in Austin in 2010 with his wife. The couple grew their family with a son in 2011, and he is very proud. “My son takes my breath away. There’s no getting used to it, and there are new adventures every day. It gives me a whole new way of looking at life.” Angel joined our Headspring team in January, and we’re happy to have him!</p>


<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="size-medium wp-image-6483 aligncenter" alt="" src="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/Angel1-200x300.jpg" width="200" height="300" /></p>


<p><b>What did you do before coming to Headspring?</b></p>


<p>I was born and raised in Puerto Rico where I went to college and graduated with a B.A. in graphic design.  I moved to Ohio when I was 21 years old. From there, I spent several years in Iowa, Kansas and Minnesota before I moved here for the long haul.</p>


<p><b>What do you love most about Austin?</b></p>


<p>The culture: laid-back, diverse, and relaxed. You can find everything from high-class restaurants to ones with a pet-friendly patio. There’s a little bit of everything for everyone.</p>


<p><b>What attracted you to Headspring?</b></p>


<p>I was attracted to the opportunity to work with a close-knit team, to the company culture, and to the opportunity to jump into the ever-changing software industry. I’m thankful for the opportunity!</p>


<p><b>How do you gauge “time well spent?"</b></p>


<p>When I’m being productive.</p>


<p><b>Who is your role model?</b></p>


<p>I would have to say my parents.  They were both very young when I was born. With no education, it must have been incredibly hard for them to raise both my sister and me, but they pulled it off.</p>


<p><b>What is your role at Headspring?</b></p>


<p>I’m a Business Development Consultant. I look for companies that would benefit from our services and who we can establish a strong business relationship with. A win-win.</p>


<p><b>What do you hope to accomplish professionally and personally in the next 5 years?</b></p>


<p>In the 11 years since Headspring was created, we have grown tremendously. I want to make sure Headspring continues to grow and expand so that every company out there knows how awesome we are.</p>


<p>Personally, I want to buy my mom a house in Puerto Rico. She is renting a small one-bedroom apartment right now and I think it’s time she has her own place again.</p>


<p><b>What do you enjoy doing in your free time?</b></p>


<p>I love watching movies and TV shows. The last movie I saw at the theater was Cabin in the Woods. I also enjoy playing video games (if I can find the time), playing my guitar, spending time with my family, going to the park and trying new restaurants. We’re foodies, and I especially love Thai food.</p>


<p><b>What’s your favorite Puerto Rican dish?</b></p>


<p>Rice, beans and chicken with fried plantains. There’s only one Puerto Rican restaurant – Chagos Restaurant – here. Their food is good but frankly, I cook better than they do, so I’m never homesick for Puerto Rican food!</p>


<p><b>What’s a tool you can’t live without?</b></p>


<p>Google Navigator, because I have a horrible sense of direction! I went to Puerto Rico during the Christmas holiday, and I got lost constantly because Google Maps doesn’t work there!</p>


<p><b>Any social media links?</b></p>


<p>Tweet me at <a href="http://twitter.com/angelrivera_pr" target="_blank">@angelrivera_pr</a>.</p>


<p>&nbsp;</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Meet Headspring: Sam Garrison]]></title>
    <link href="http://headspringlabs.com/blog/meet-headspring-sam-garrison/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-08T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://headspringlabs.com/blog/meet-headspring-sam-garrison</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Born in Kentucky and raised in Austin, Sam Garrison can be found on Lake Austin on the weekends, sailing on his 12-foot Laser. After graduating from The University of Texas at Austin with degrees in government and history, he joined the army for about a year. We’re excited to introduce Sam to you!</p>


<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="size-medium wp-image-6480 aligncenter" alt="sam1" src="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/sam1-263x300.jpg" width="263" height="300" /></p>


<p><b>What did you do before coming to Headspring?</b></p>


<p>I worked at a pharmaceutical research company and analyzed statistics, trends, patterns, and data. I enjoy working with numbers, so joining Headspring’s Business Development department was a great fit.</p>


<p><b>What attracted you to work at Headspring?</b></p>


<p>Great corporate culture. Headspring recruits highly talented people and the opportunity to work around very intelligent people made it appealing. The job description and career progression are very straightforward and match my career goals.</p>


<p><b>How do you gauge “time well spent?”</b></p>


<p>Any time you look back and say you wouldn’t have done it differently, or doing something you enjoy that also brings long-term goodness or benefit.<em id="__mceDel"> </em></p>


<p><b>What is your role at Headspring?</b></p>


<p>I’m focused on developing business in the Houston market. I’m defining and developing the working markets and building relationships with existing and potential clients.</p>


<p><b>What do you hope to accomplish professionally and personally in the next 5 years?</b></p>


<p>I care about Headspring and am invested in the company and people. I want to help Headspring grow. I also want to grow and increase my level of responsibility.</p>


<p><b>What do you enjoy doing in your free time?</b></p>


<p>I love sports and watch ESPN a lot. Besides sailing, I play in a lacrosse league. I also enjoy playing chess, reading and all outdoor activities.</p>


<p><b>What’s a tool or gadget you can’t live without?</b></p>


<p>My headlamp. It’s invaluable when you’re in the dark. I always have it with me. I used it to change a sparkplug under the car hood the other day.</p>


<p><b>What’s a piece of wisdom or advice you live by?</b></p>


<p>I don’t believe things happen for a reason but I believe in making the best of the situation when it does happen.</p>


<p>&nbsp;</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Meet Headspring: Joe Lockbaum]]></title>
    <link href="http://headspringlabs.com/blog/meet-headspring-joe-lockbaum/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-01T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://headspringlabs.com/blog/meet-headspring-joe-lockbaum</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: left;">In January, we welcomed Joe Lockbaum to the Business Development department of the Headspring Team. Joe moved to Austin from New Jersey in the summer of 2012 for our wonderful weather -- “You don’t have to shovel heat!” Moving with his wife, Joe was excited to continue his career in the great Texas economy and in a great city. In addition to working at Headspring, Joe is in the process of starting a gym.</p>


<p><img class="size-medium wp-image-6470 aligncenter" alt="20130208_121916" src="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/20130208_121916-204x300.jpg" width="204" height="300" /><b>What was your life before Headspring?</b></p>


<p>I worked for Bloomberg, a financial data and news provider, for 12 years. The first 9 years were spent in several roles selling and building the Professional software for financial professionals.  The last 3 years were spent in Enterprise Products group, selling real-time feeds and data management products to the largest clients.</p>


<p>&nbsp;</p>


<p><b>What attracted you to work at Headspring?</b></p>


<p>The people. There are a lot of software firms in Austin, and my experience made the industry a good fit.  But the culture and the people I met through the interview process with Headspring, and being part of a team of very smart people – people clearly much smarter than me - makes me feel good about where I’m sitting, and very confident I made the right choice.</p>


<p>&nbsp;</p>


<p><b>How do you gauge “time well spent?”</b></p>


<p>I’m extremely numbers-oriented and methodical. I find gratification in building something out of my efforts and seeing the results in dollars and cents.</p>


<p>&nbsp;</p>


<p><b>What role do you play at Headspring?</b></p>


<p>Pretty simple, really, my role at Headspring includes prospecting, reaching out to potential clients, and bringing those clients in the door. Whatever I can do to put projects on the board.</p>


<p>&nbsp;</p>


<p><b>What do you hope to accomplish professionally and personally in the next 5 years?</b></p>


<p>Professionally, I want to help grow Headspring by bringing in new business. I want to put Headspring in a difficult position by bringing in so much business that the company doesn’t know what to do with it all. I also want to become a principal leader in the company. On a personal level, my wife and I are looking forward to starting a family.</p>


<p>&nbsp;</p>


<p><b>What do you enjoy doing in your free time?</b></p>


<p>I love talking to random people to hear their stories – about how they spend their time and how they make money. When my wife and I go out to eat, we always sit at the bar and talk to every single person that walks through the door. We like to engage multiple people and try to get the whole bar talking.</p>


<p>&nbsp;</p>


<p>My favorite places are airport bars. There are some really great people with some really amazing stories to tell.  One time, at the Heathrow airport, I started talking to someone in the first-class lounge (where you tend to meet very interesting and accomplished people). He said he liked to tell people he owned a company called Royal Ice and that he sold chunks of glaciers to Saudi princes in the desert. He then told me he really leased jets to corporate executives. We had a great laugh!</p>


<p>&nbsp;</p>


<p><b>What’s something you can’t live without?</b></p>


<p>Other than my phone – definitely my gym bag.  I like working out and lifting; it’s my ‘me’ time.  It’s an opportunity to shut down my mind for a little bit.  I get some of my better ideas/plans when I’m able to clear my mind of the noise.</p>


<p>&nbsp;</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Get to Know a Developer: Jose Basilio]]></title>
    <link href="http://headspringlabs.com/blog/get-to-know-a-developer-jose-basilio/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-11T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://headspringlabs.com/blog/get-to-know-a-developer-jose-basilio</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="alignright size-medium wp-image-6321" alt="Jose Basilio" src="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/photo-2-e1357940416657-224x300.jpg" width="224" height="300" />This week we welcomed Jose Basilio to the team! Jose currently lives in Houston, but he’s originally from the Dominican Republic. I was so excited to speak with him because he told me that participating in <a href="http://www.headspring.com/mary/headspring-hosts-central-texas-givecamp-to-benefit-10-local-non-profits/" target="_blank">CTX GiveCamp</a> (one of my projects last year) convinced him to look into working for us full time. In fact, Jose was on the TX Kidney Foundation team, which won CTX GiveCamp’s highest honor: the “Meg Ryan Facelift Award for Coolest UI”. I knew he was a winner. Here’s the rest of our conversation:</p>


<p>Where did you work, and what did you do before coming to Headspring?</p>


<p>I was a senior developer at Dril-Quip, Inc., a manufacturer of oil and gas drilling equipment in Houston. Prior to that, I worked in various roles in application and database administration at Compaq / HP.</p>


<p>What or who made you want to work here?</p>


<p>Throughout my career, I have worked for companies where software was a cost-center. I wanted the opportunity to work for a company where my efforts directly contribute to the bottom-line. I also wanted work along-size like-minded individuals that have a passion for learning and moving their careers forward. I believe Headspring is that company.</p>


<p>What led you to software development?</p>


<p>Computers are better than humans at performing repetitive tasks in a fast and consistent manner. I wanted to automate my day-to-day activities as a database admin. This led me to learn scripting languages, and I enjoyed that so much that moved into full-blown development.</p>


<p>What did you learn first?</p>


<p>I started by learning VBScript to create windows scripts and dynamic web pages back in the day.</p>


<p>Do you like teaching?</p>


<p>I love teaching and learning new things. The best way to truly learn and become an expert at something is to teach it.  I think that in the process of simplifying a topic in order to teach it to others, we gain clarity of mind and reach those “aha” moments in our understanding of the subject.</p>


<p>&nbsp;</p>


<p>Want to know more? Tweet <a href="https://twitter.com/jbasilio" target="_blank">@jbasilio</a>.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Get to Know a Developer: Patrick Abbs]]></title>
    <link href="http://headspringlabs.com/blog/get-to-know-a-developer-patrick-abbs/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-08T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://headspringlabs.com/blog/get-to-know-a-developer-patrick-abbs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="alignright size-medium wp-image-6318" title="Patrick Abbs" src="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/photo-1-e1357685470139-224x300.jpg" alt="Patrick Abbs" width="224" height="300" />This week we welcomed in a New Year and a new consultant to the team: Patrick Abbs.  Patrick is a native Austinite, but just moved back from New York.  He went to NYU for Individualized Study – a new type of customized undergraduate degree program. He explained to me that he chose a focus of study (Game Theory) and developed his own course schedule around it. He had to produce a senior thesis and submit it before a board, similar to the process of obtaining a graduate degree.</p>


<p>In school and in the workforce, he found programming knowledge to be very helpful in crunching data for statistical analysis. Eventually, he was led to Headspring. Read more about how that happened:</p>


<p><strong>Where did you work, and what did you do before coming to Headspring?</strong></p>


<p>My last two jobs were completely different from each other, but Headspring is interestingly kind of a mix between the two.  At the tech startup Tilde, I worked with the LAMP stack (as well as some C# and Python) to create a B-to-B tool for businesses to streamline their back-office processes.  At DRSdigital, I worked directly with new and existing clients to create, customize, and maintain secure data rooms (typically for potential merger and acquisition deals).</p>


<p><strong>Are you an expert at anything?</strong></p>


<p>I have worked extensively with algorithms geared towards statistical analysis of information sets, and am especially well-acquainted with mixture models (a more specific type of statistical algorithm).  As much as I love statistics algorithms, though, I definitely want to expand my expertise into other areas of programming.  At the moment I'm fascinated with the differences between and advantages of different types of databases, as well as with how compilers work.</p>


<p><strong>What led you to software development?</strong></p>


<p>The initial appeal of software development for me came from the recognition that once a program has been written to solve a given type of problem once, it can thereafter solve any instance of that problem an endless number of times with incredible efficiency and little effort.  For instance, it might take me two minutes to sort fifty documents according to some ordering criteria manually, versus ten minutes to write a program which executes the same sorting methodology.  However, after I have written such a program I can use it to sort any number of documents any number of times in a matter of milliseconds for each execution, all with the click of a button.  Once I started thinking about software development as something that requires some initial time investment but can save exponentially more time in the long run, I was hooked.</p>


<p><strong>What did you learn first?</strong></p>


<p>My first introduction to code was as a mathematically-oriented person trying to convey algorithms to software developers for implementation.  The fact that I had no experience with code and the developers I was working with had a limited understanding of math significantly slowed the rate at which theory could be converted to practice, so I decided to try to bridge the gap between our areas of understanding by learning the relatively simple, mathematical language Python.</p>


<p><strong>What or who made you want to work here?</strong></p>


<p>Headspring is an appealing place to work for me for several reasons.  It is known for having a great and open company culture (which I saw first-hand at the two lunch-and-learns I've attended).  I'm also excited about the fact that the vast majority of the people working there are seasoned, experienced professionals, and as a less experienced developer I really value being able to ask questions and learn from the experience of the people around me.</p>


<p>As far as the actual responsibilities of being a Headspring consultant, I really like the fact that the projects are diverse and let me work on a variety of different programming challenges.  Finally, I like the fact that working at Headspring often involves working directly with clients.  I love technology, but regularly interacting with clients is exciting to me.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
