<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: sxswi | Headspring Labs]]></title>
  <link href="http://headspringlabs.com/blog/categories/sxswi/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://headspringlabs.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-24T19:08:18-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://headspringlabs.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Headspring Labs]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Make the Most of SXSWi for Free]]></title>
    <link href="http://headspringlabs.com/blog/make-the-most-of-sxswi-for-free/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-06T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://headspringlabs.com/blog/make-the-most-of-sxswi-for-free</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The second week of March is upon us, and I could not be more excited.</p>


<p>SXSW Interactive is going to be bigger and better than ever – over 19,000 are expected to attend this year.   I’m really looking forward to being a part of it.  Even the Juggalos will be there!  Juggalos and Bruce Springsteen featured in the same event; I never thought I would see the day.</p>


<p>If you have a badge, make sure to find me and say hello. In between panels, I plan to visit the Microsoft and Beacon Lounges or browse the Trade Show and ScreenBurn Arcade.  Here’s my schedule:   <a href="http://schedule.sxsw.com/2012/user_events/user_60347">http://schedule.sxsw.com/2012/user_events/user_60347</a></p>


<p>However, if you don’t have badge, there is still plenty of opportunity to get in on the action.  Of course, I’ve made a list:</p>


<p><strong>Thursday, March 8<sup>th</sup>: </strong><a href="http://door64.com/sxsw2012">Door64 Pre-SXSW Interactive Party</a></p>


<p>Techies don’t usually need a party to prove how fun they are, but an open bar sponsored by Dell, Intel, and CyrusOne never hurts.  Along with free booze, there will be two bands, and Dell is giving out free laptops and other devices for door prizes. Tickets are cheap ($20) and half off if you’re an Austin Cloud User Goup member.  A steal of a deal!</p>


<p><strong>Friday, March 9<sup>th</sup>:</strong> <a href="https://www.facebook.com/events/301931889872103">Refresh Austin’s SXSW Kickoff Lunch</a></p>


<p>For the fourth year in a row, Refresh Austin has organized an opportunity for folks to mingle and catch up with Refreshers from all over the world.  It’s not sponsored, so you’ll have to pick up your own tab.  However, this is a great opportunity to meet up with badge-holding friends from out-of-town, and convince them to get a job at your company in Austin!</p>


<p><strong>Sunday, March 11<sup>th</sup>: </strong><a href="http://www.eventida.com/events/2012_dewey_ceremony_air-interactive_awards/#SXSWparty">Dewey Awards Ceremony</a></p>


<p>This event is also free, and is co-presented by our friends at Knowbility.  The party will honor 10 media do-gooders with tons of food, drink, and music.  Also, Knowbility will announce the winners for SXSW Interactive AIR.  We’re keeping our fingers crossed for the team of Headspringers that participated in the competition!</p>


<p><strong>Monday, March 12<sup>th</sup>: </strong><a href="http://garann.com/allgirlhacknight/2012/cli.html">Austin All-Girl Dev Brunch</a></p>


<p>The Austin All-Girl Hack Night and Girl Develop It groups have organized a brunch for techie chicks to get together and celebrate their awesomeness.  This year, Headspring is sponsoring because 1) we love All Girl Hack Night 2) we really love the Bloody Mary’s at Frank.  If you’re a girl and you love to code, I strongly encourage you to check this one out. And it’s totally free!</p>


<p>As always, we’ll continue to keep our community events calendar updated with these events and more.</p>


<p>If you know of any other non-badge required events going on during sxswi, please post in our comments.  Happy hunting!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
