<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: learning | Headspring Labs]]></title>
  <link href="http://headspringlabs.com/blog/categories/learning/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://headspringlabs.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-24T19:08:18-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://headspringlabs.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Headspring Labs]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jack Welch MBA–a new graduate]]></title>
    <link href="http://headspringlabs.com/blog/jack-welch-mbaa-new-graduate/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-12T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://headspringlabs.com/blog/jack-welch-mbaa-new-graduate</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img style="margin: 0px 15px 5px 0px; display: inline; float: left" alt="Jack Welch Management Institute" align="left" src="http://www.jwmi.com/sites/all/themes/jwmi/images/jwmi-logo.png">For the last two years, I have been enrolled in the <a href="http://www.jwmi.com">Jack Welch Management Institute</a>.&nbsp; I just finished their <a href="http://www.jwmi.com/content/executive-mba-course-descriptions">Executive MBA program</a>, and my perspective has changed.&nbsp; First, I have to thank <a href="https://twitter.com/jack_welch">Jack Welch</a> for creating this program, in which he shares his decades of business leadership experience.&nbsp; </p>


<p>If you aren’t familiar, Jack Welch was the CEO of <a href="http://www.ge.com/">General Electric</a> from 1981 to 2001.&nbsp; That’s a lot of years!&nbsp;&nbsp; Now, he shares his knowledge and experience with people like me – and whoever else enrolls in his MBA program.</p>


<p><img style="margin: 5px 0px 5px 5px; display: inline; float: right" alt="Logo-strayer.png" align="right" src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/2/2f/Logo-strayer.png">JWMI is a program hosted at <a href="http://www.strayer.edu/">Strayer University</a>, which is a nationwide university that has been around since 1892 – not as old as my alma mater, <a href="http://www.tamu.edu/">Texas A&amp;M</a> (1872/6), but very proven.&nbsp; Chances are there is a Strayer location in a city near you.</p>


<p>I was very fortunate to have a great classmate who took the courses with me.&nbsp; <a href="http://headspring.com/kevin">Kevin Hurwitz</a>, the Chief Architect at <a href="http://www.headspring.com/">Headspring</a>, also just received his MBA from JWMI.&nbsp; Each course, we were able to swap notes and apply the knowledge every week at Headspring.</p>


<p>Throughout the two years, I completed courses on a broad range of topics.&nbsp; They are listed here.&nbsp; As I blog about what I have learned and applied in each course, I’ll link to that blog from this list.</p>


<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.headspring.com/jeffrey/jack-welch-mba-course-business-communication-and-ethics/">Business Communications and Ethics</a>
<li>Leading in the 21st Century
<li>Strategy
<li>People Management
<li>Marketing in a Global Environment
<li>Managerial Economics
<li>Operations Management
<li>Financial Management I
<li>Organizational Change and Culture
<li>Financial Management II
<li>New Business Ventures and Entrepreneurship
<li>Capstone (simulation)</li>
</ul>


<p>I am very happy to have attended and graduated from the Jack Welch Management Institute.&nbsp; My contribution to Headspring has materially benefited from the learning.&nbsp; Also, I am so excited that several other Headspringers have decided to enroll for this semester!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Improve developer productivity by losing your mouse]]></title>
    <link href="http://headspringlabs.com/blog/improve-developer-productivity-by-losing-your-mouse/"/>
    <updated>2011-08-31T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://headspringlabs.com/blog/improve-developer-productivity-by-losing-your-mouse</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I started my development career working for a very small company that developed accessibility software for the blind. I was fresh out of school and working on a screen reader for Windows 3.1. It was quite a challenge, in more ways than one.</p>


<p>One of the things I had to learn was how blind people used the computer at all. My boss (the owner of the company) was blind and taught me a lot – but he could only work in DOS, as there just weren’t any screen readers for Windows yet. So I had to figure out a lot of things on my own.</p>


<p><a href="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/08/image.png"><img style="margin: 0px 30px 25px 0px; padding-left: 0px; padding-right: 0px; float: left; padding-top: 0px; border: 0px;" src="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/08/image_thumb.png" alt="image" width="165" height="169" align="left" border="0" /></a>As you might guess, blind people have terrible eye-hand coordination, so they never use a mouse. I decided that I would also learn to avoid my mouse as much as possible. One of the best things for me was to just push the mouse out of reach – if it wasn’t there, it made it more inconvenient to use it. Sometimes I would go so far as disconnecting it or dropping down behind my desk. I very quickly learned that the Alt key would let me get to menus, and that the tab key would move me between controls in a dialog. I learned that the Enter key in a dialog would (usually) press the default button, which looked different than other buttons. Over time, I developed a very strong ability to use nothing but the keyboard – and it has helped in many ways.</p>


<p>One thing I noticed as I moved on to other jobs is that many developers had not learned the same keyboard skills that I had. I would frequently wince as I watched someone use the mouse to do something, and then I would gently suggest the (much faster) keyboard way of doing the same thing. One time I was working with someone on a word processing document, and they wanted to change the font of the whole document. I t was painful to watch them first click on the up arrow in the scroll bar to get to the top of the document, then use the mouse to select the whole document. They thought it was pretty cool when I showed them that CTRL+A almost always works to “select all”. One of my other favorites is that when I am filling in a form on a website, when it gets to asking about my address, there is almost always a huge dropdown for State. Since I live in Texas, hitting T twice gets me right where I need to be super-fast. You can also do this for those “what year were you born in” dropdowns – rather than pointing and clicking, just start typing, and it will select the right year.</p>


<p>Pair programming is a great way to share these kinds of tips and tricks. Attending a coding dojo is another one. Of course, the <a href="http://www.headspring.com/services/developer-training">Headspring training classes</a> usually introduce students to all kinds of productivity enhancing techniques too!</p>


<p>There are too many keyboard shortcuts to list here, but start looking around for lists of keyboard shortcuts for the programs you use most often. Use something like <a href="http://osherove.com/tools">Key Jedi</a> when you pair with someone so you can learn they shortcuts they use. and try ‘losing’ your mouse every once in a while to force yourself out of your comfort zone. It may take longer at first, but when you master them, you will be faster than ever.</p>


<p>Here are a few keyboard shortcut references to get you started:</p>


<p><a href="http://support.microsoft.com/kb/126449">Keyboard Shortcuts for Windows</a> – a nice general list to get you started.</p>


<p><a href="http://windows.microsoft.com/en-US/windows7/Keyboard-shortcuts">Windows 7 Shortcuts</a> – some duplicates here, but some things that are Windows 7 specific.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
