<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: notepad | Headspring Labs]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.headspringlabs.com/blog/categories/notepad/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.headspringlabs.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-27T15:36:16-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.headspringlabs.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Headspring Labs]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Notepad Will Corrupt Your Data]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.headspringlabs.com/blog/notepad-will-corrupt-your-data/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.headspringlabs.com/blog/notepad-will-corrupt-your-data</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Summary</h2>


<p>The notepad.exe built into Windows will silently convert characters represented in binary as all zeros into spaces.  Don't use notepad to edit files that contain ANY binary data, such as digital signatures.  There are other editors that will not convert the null characters, I use and recommend Notepad++.</p>


<h2>Observing the Issue</h2>


<p>Recently I worked on a development project involving cryptography and digital signatures.  If you aren't familiar with digital signatures, they can be briefly described as a way to securely "sign" some content so a receiver can verify that the content actually came from a particular verified party.  This is very useful since electronic communication, unlike face to face communication, offers little innate assurance of whom you're speaking with.  You definitely want some assurance an electronic message that says "sell all your stock" actually came from your broker! If you'd like to learn more about how digital signatures work, try doing some internet searches on "public key encryption" or "public key cryptography".</p>


<p>One approach to digital signatures is using a single file with both the content being signed and the signature itself (technical background: I was processing AS2 messages, but that's not important to the discussion).  Here's a simple example of a short text message with a corresponding signature for it (although you could sign other media types like sound or picture files).  We can see the plain text message, and some of the signature itself is just plain text.  But because this is binary it has bytes that are all zero, which in text is represented as a null character.  Notepad++ shows these as NUL, but Notepad converts them into regular spaces.</p>


<p>(screenshots from each)</p>


<p><a href="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/asignedMessageInNpp.png"><img style="padding-left: 0px; padding-right: 0px; padding-top: 0px; border: 0px;" src="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/asignedMessageInNpp_thumb.png" alt="Simple digital signature in Notepad++.  Null characters are visible." width="244" height="135" border="0" /></a>    <a href="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/asignedMessageInNotepad.png"><img style="padding-left: 0px; padding-right: 0px; padding-top: 0px; border: 0px;" src="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/asignedMessageInNotepad_thumb.png" alt="Simple digital signature in Notepad.exe.  Null characters are turned into spaces." width="244" height="120" border="0" /></a></p>


<p>Here's what happens when we save this digital signature with notepad.exe.  When we reopen it in Notepad++, we can see that notepad converted the null characters into spaces.</p>


<p><a href="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/acorruptedInNpp.png"><img style="padding-left: 0px; padding-right: 0px; padding-top: 0px; border: 0px;" src="http://www.headspring.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/acorruptedInNpp_thumb.png" alt="Signature in Notepad++ after it was saved by Notepad.exe.  Null characters have been converted into spaces." width="244" height="127" border="0" /></a></p>


<p>The binary data is now corrupted.  Bytes of all zero aren't significant in text because they represent a null character that no one is going to miss, or even usually see.  They are very significant in binary data, however. In this particular case, when the null characters are changed the signature will no longer validate because it has been altered, a potential sign of tampering.</p>


<p>There are two lessons here.  The first is not to be lulled into thinking binary data can be treated as text, even if a lot of it LOOKS like text.  The second is don't ever, ever use notepad with binary data.  My personal preference is to never, ever use notepad anyway; I ran into this issue when I received some signatures from someone else.  There are so many better alternatives available like Notepad++, Sublime, e, Notepad2, Ultraedit...well, you get the idea.  Find one that works for you and throw away notepad.exe!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
